<doc id="texml.index">
	<title>TeXML: an XML vocabulary for TeX</title>
	<p>TeXML is an XML vocabulary for TeX. A processor translates TeXML source into TeX.</p>
	<table border="1" width="100%">
		<caption>Example of TeXML to TeX translation</caption>
		<tr>
			<th width="50%">TeXML</th>
			<th>TeX</th>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td>
<lst><![CDATA[<cmd name="documentclass">
  <opt>12pt</opt>
  <parm>letter</parm>
</cmd>]]></lst>
			</td>
			<td>
<lst>\documentclass[12pt]{letter}</lst>
			</td>
		</tr>
	</table>
	<p>One of the main benefits of TeXML usage is an automatical translation of the TeX special symbols.</p>
	<table border="1" width="100%">
		<caption>Example of translation of special TeX symbols</caption>
		<tr>
			<th width="50%">TeXML</th>
			<th>TeX</th>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td><lst>&lt;TeXML&gt;\section{No&amp;#xa0;break}&lt;/TeXML&gt;</lst></td>
			<td><lst>$\backslash$section\{No~break\}</lst></td>
		</tr>
	</table>
	<p>The TeXML processor supports different output encodings and escapes out-of-encoding chars automatically.</p>
	<table border="1" width="100%">
		<caption>Example of translation of non-ASCII characters</caption>
		<tr>
			<th width="38%" align="left">TeXML</th>
			<td><lst>&lt;TeXML&gt;&amp;#x422;&amp;#x435;&amp;#x425;&lt;/TeXML&gt;</lst></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<th align="left">TeX in ASCII encoding</th>
			<td><lst>\cyrchar\CYRT \cyrchar\cyre \cyrchar\CYRH </lst></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<th align="left">TeX in Russian encoding</th>
			<td><lst>TeX</lst></td>
		</tr>
	</table>
	<p>There is a <a href="spec.html">TeXML specification</a>. DTD is included into the distribution.</p>
	<p>Rationalities and objectives of TeXML were presented by Douglas Lovell at the Tex Users Group meeting in 1999. His paper is available online on TUG site: &#8220;<a href="http://www.tug.org/TUG99-web/pdf/lovell.pdf">TeXML: Typesetting XML with TeX</a>&#8221; (PDF, 180 Kb).</p>
	<p>There was TeXMLatt&#xE9;, a Java implementation of <a href="http://www.alphaworks.ibm.com/tech/texml">TeXML by IBM alphaWorks</a>, but now this realization &#8220;has been retired&#8221;. There is also <a href="http://www.bluweb.com/us/chouser/proj/texmlapis/">TeXMLapis</a> by Chris Houser, a Perl implementation of TeXML.</p>
	<sect>
		<title>Getting TeXML</title>
		<p>The TeXML processor is a Python script. You need <a href="http://python.org/">Python</a> 2.3 run the script. Additional modules are not required.</p>
		<p>You can download Python TeXML in the SourceForge <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=102261"> project download area</a>. A distribution archive with extension <tt>.tar.gz</tt> is a package for Unix and with <tt>.zip</tt> is for Windows. The only difference between them is in line endings (Unix or DOS style).</p>
		<p>Current version is 0.95 beta. Although it is marked as beta, bugs are not expected and the processor should work well.</p>
		<p>The software is released under the <a href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html"> GNU Public License</a>.</p>
		<p>Support is available through the SourceForge <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/getfo/"> project area</a> (TeXML is a part of the GetFO project).</p>
	</sect>
</doc>
