<doc id="texml.thesis">
  <title>TeXML: an XML vocabulary for TeX</title>
  <p>Thesis of the talk at the First International Conference of Open-Source Developers, Obninsk, Russia, 2004. Author: Oleg Paraschenko, Saint Petersburg.</p>
  <blockquote><p>Abstract. The paper describes one of the methods of publishing XML documents through LaTeX. We propose to use TeXML, an intermediate presentation of TeX notation in an XML format.</p></blockquote>

  <sect>
    <title>The need for TeXML</title>
    <p>TeXML<a href="#texml">[1]</a> is an intermediate presentation of TeX notation in an XML format. TeXML simplifies creation of printable versions of documents when the following conditions are true:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>original documents are in XML format,</li>
      <li>printable versions are being created by LaTeX, and</li>
      <li>XSLT is the best language for XML transformations.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>There are several projects(<a href="#tbook">[2]</a>, <a href="#xsltml">[3]</a>, <a href="#dblatex">[4]</a>, <a href="#db2latex">[5]</a>) that transform XML to LaTeX using XSLT. All of these projects have the same problem: XSLT is very inefficient when the result of an XSLT transformation is not XML.</p>
    <p>This problem can be solved using an intermediate step. First, XSLT efficiently transforms XML into TeXML, and then a TeXML processor turns TeXML into the TeX format.</p>
  </sect>

  <sect>
    <title>Brief overview of TeXML</title>
    <p>An example to demonstrate the basic syntax of TeXML:</p>
<pre><![CDATA[<TeXML>
 <cmd name="documentclass">
  <opt>a4paper</opt>
  <parm>minimal</parm>
 </cmd>
 <env name="document">
  Eto&nbsp;&mdash; primer.
 </env>
</TeXML>]]></pre>
<p>The results after processing:</p>
<pre><![CDATA[\begin{verbatim}
\documentclass[a4paper]{minimal}
\begin{document}
Eto~\textemdash{} primer.
\end{document}]]></pre>
    <p>The main tasks of the processor:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>escaping of the TeX special characters (for example, escaping &#x201c;<tt>&lt;</tt>&#x201d; to &#x201c;<tt>\textless</tt>&#x201d;),</li>
      <li>unicode processing (for example, printing russian letter &#x201c;<tt>d</tt>&#x201d; as is or as &#x201c;<tt>\cyrchar\cyrd{}</tt>&#x201d;),</li>
      <li>disjoining of ligatures (for example, replacing &#x201c;<tt>---</tt>&#x201d; by &#x201c;<tt>-{}-{}-</tt>&#x201d;), and</li>
      <li>avoiding empty lines in TeX output.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>In addition to these essential transformations, TeXML also provides extended functionality.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>The TeXML language reflects the structured constructions of LaTeX such as environments or commands with parameters.</li>
      <li>Automatic layout of TeX code into nice human-readable documents.</li>
    </ul>
  </sect>

  <sect>
    <title>TeXML benefits</title>
    <p>A simple TeXML code</p>
<pre><![CDATA[<group><cmd name="it" gr="0"/>\example</group>]]></pre>
<p>corresponds to a TeX fragment</p>
    <pre>{\it \textbackslash{}example}</pre>
    <p>There are several projects that create LaTeX from XML using XSLT, for example: tbook<a href="#tbook">[2]</a>, xsltml<a href="#xsltml">[3]</a>, dblatex<a href="#dblatex">[4]</a>, db2latex<a href="#db2latex">[5]</a>. Usage of these projects demonstrates the following problems when generating the TeX fragment:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>special symbols are not escaped,</li>
      <li>space after a command name is missed (getting &#x201c;<tt>\it<i>text</i></tt>&#x201d; instead of &#x201c;<tt>\it&#xa0;<i>text</i></tt>&#x201d;),</li>
      <li>opening or closing brace is lost,</li>
      <li>only latin-1 encoding is supported.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>These and some other problems do not appear when using TeXML.</p>
  </sect>

  <sect>
    <title>Other versions of TeXML</title>
    <p>During my search for a solution for XML publishing through LaTeX, I found that Douglas Lovell introduced<a href="#lovell">[6]</a> the TeXML approach in the year 1999, and there was even an implementation in Java. This project, TeXMLatt&#xE9;<a href="#texmlatte">[7]</a>, was abandoned some time ago, but its specification survived. Our TeXML is heavely based on this specification.</p>
    <p>There is also TeXMLapis<a href="#texmlapis">[8]</a>, a Perl-processor of a subset of TeXML, but its functionality is limited.</p>
  </sect>

  <sect>
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <ol>
      <li><a name="texml"/> TeXML: an XML vocabulary for TeX <a href="http://getfo.org/texml/">http://getfo.org/texml/</a></li>
      <li><a name="tbook"/> The tbook system for XML Authoring <a href="http://tbookdtd.sourceforge.net/">http://tbookdtd.sourceforge.net/</a></li>
      <li><a name="xsltml"/> XSLT MathML Library <a href="http://xsltml.sourceforge.net/">http://xsltml.sourceforge.net/</a></li>
      <li><a name="dblatex"/> DocBook to LaTeX/ConTeXt Publishing <a href="http://dblatex.sourceforge.net/">http://dblatex.sourceforge.net/</a></li>
      <li><a name="db2latex"/> DB2LaTeX XSL Stylesheets <a href="http://db2latex.sourceforge.net/">http://db2latex.sourceforge.net/</a></li>
      <li><a name="lovell"/> Douglas Lovell, TeXML: Typesetting XML with TeX <a href="http://www.tug.org/TUG99-web/pdf/lovell.pdf">http://www.tug.org/TUG99-web/pdf/lovell.pdf</a></li>
      <li><a name="texmlatte"/> TeXMLatt&#xE9; <a href="http://www.alphaworks.ibm.com/tech/texml">http://www.alphaworks.ibm.com/tech/texml</a></li>
      <li><a name="texmlapis"/> TeXMLapis <a href="http://www.bluweb.com/us/chouser/proj/texmlapis/">http://www.bluweb.com/us/chouser/proj/texmlapis/</a></li>
    </ol>
  </sect>
</doc>
